

# Avishek Anand

# Assistant Professor

#### Research Interests and Profile

I work on problems relating to Information retrieval, NLP and Web Mining. I am currently an Assistant Professor in the Intelligent Systems department in Leibniz University, Hannover. I am recently interested in topic involving **interpretability of Information Retrieval systems** and **Scaling unsupervised representations of discrete structures**. I teach topics relating to information retrieval, big data and machine learning and also advise students at the Masters and PhD level.

#### Education

2009–2013 **Ph.D. Student**, Max Planck Institute for Informatics (MPI) and Saarland University, Saarbrücken, Germany.

Thesis Title: Indexing Methods for Web Archives

2007–2008 **M.Sc. in Computer Science**, MPII and Saarland University, Saarbrücken, Germany. Graduated with Honors

2002–2005 **B.Tech. in Information Technology**, Indian Institute of Information technology, Allahabad, India.

Graduated with Honors

### Professional Experience

2014-2017 **Post-doctoral researcher** and **Project Leader** in **L3S Research Center** headed by Prof. Wolfgang Nejdl.

2005-2007 **Microsoft Research and Development Center, India**Software Engineer in the Internet Explorer 7 team, Windows Group.

2004-2005 **Lucent Technologies, India.**Research Intern, Core Switching Division.

# Publications (Selected Full Papers)

2019 Avishek Anand, Megha Khosla, Jaspreet Singh, Jan-Hendrik Zab and Zijian Zhang. Asynchronous Training of Word Embeddings for large text corpora. In: Proceedings of the Conference on Web Search and Data Mining (WSDM 2019).

- Jaspreet Singh, Avishek Anand. EXS: Explainable Search Using Local Model Agnostic Interpretability. In: Proceedings of the Conference on Web Search and Data Mining (WSDM 2019).
- Besnik Fetahu, Avishek Anand, Maria Koutraki. . **TableNet: An approach for determining fine-grained relations for Wikipedia tables**. In: Proceedings of Conference on The World Wide Web. (The WebConf 2019).
- 2018 Jaspreet Singh, Avishek Anand. Posthoc Interpretability of Learning to Rank Models using Secondary Training Data. In: Proceedings of Workshop on ExplainAble Recommendation and Search. 2018.
  - Helge Holzmann, Megha Khosla, *Avishek Anand*. **Delusive Page Rank of Incomlete Graphs**. In: *Proceedings of Complex Networks. 2018*.
  - Avishek Anand Kilian Bizer, Alexander Erlei, Ujwal Gadiraju, Christian Heinze, Lukas Meub, Wolfgang Nejdl and Bjoern Steinroetter. **Effects of Algorithmic Decision-Making and Interpretability on Human Behavior: Experiments using Crowdsourcing.** In: *Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Human Computation and Crowdsourcing.* (HCOMP 2018).
- 2017 Besnik Fetahu, Katja Markert, Wolfgang Nejdl, Avishek Anand. Fine-Grained Citation Span Detection for References in Wikipedia. In: Proceedings of the Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP 2017).
  - Vinay Setty, Abhijit Anand, Arunav Mishra, *Avishek Anand*. **Modeling Event Importance for Ranking Daily News Events.** In: *Proceedings of the Conference on Web Search and Data Mining (WSDM 2017)*.
  - Helge Holzmann, Wolfgang Nejdl, **Avishek Anand**. Exploring Web Archives Through Temporal Anchor Texts. Published in: Proceedings of WebScience 2017.
- 2016 Besnik Fetahu, Katja Markert, Wolfgang Nejdl, Avishek Anand. Finding News Citations for Wikipedia. In: Proceedings of the 19th ACM Conference on Information and Knowledge Management (CIKM 2016).
  - Jaspreet Singh, Johannes Hoffart, Avishek Anand. Discovering Entities with Just a Little Help from You. In: Proceedings of the 19th ACM Conference on Information and Knowledge Management (CIKM 2016).
  - Helge Holzmann, Vinay Goel, *Avishek Anand*. **ArchiveSpark: Efficient Web Archive Access, Extraction and Derivation**. In: *Proceedings of the ACM/IEEE-CS Joint Conference on Digital Libraries (JCDL 2016)*
  - Helge Holzmann, Wolfgang Nejdl, *Avishek Anand*. **The Dawn of Today's Popular Domains: A Study of the Archived German Web over 18 Years**. In: *Proceedings of the ACM/IEEE-CS Joint Conference on Digital Libraries (JCDL 2016)*
  - Jaspreet Singh, Wolfgang Nejdl, Avishek Anand. History by Diversity: Helping Historians Search News Archives. In: Proceedings of the ACM SIGIR Conference on Human Information Interaction and Retrieval (CHIIR 2016).
- 2015 Besnik Fetahu, Katja Markert, Avishek Anand. Automated News Suggestions for Populating Wikipedia Entity Pages. In: Proceedings of the 19th ACM Conference on Information and Knowledge Management (CIKM 2015).

Tuan Tran, Nattiya Kahnabua, Claudia Niederee, *Avishek Anand.* Balancing Novelty and Salience: Adaptive Learning to Rank Entities for Timeline Summarization of High-impact Events. In: *Proceedings of the 19th ACM Conference on Information and Knowledge Management (CIKM 2015).* 

Besnik Fetahu, Abhijit Anand, **Avishek Anand**. How much is Wikipedia Lagging Behind News?. Published in: Proceedings of WebScience 2015, Oxford.

Evica Milchevski, *Avishek Anand*, Sebastian Michel. **The Sweet Spot between Inverted Indices and Metric-Space Indexing for Top-K-List Similarity Search**. Published in: *Proceedings of the Extended Databases Technology (EDBT 2015)*.

Before 2014 Stephan Seufert, *Avishek Anand*, Srikanta Bedathur, Gerhard Weikum. **FERRARI: Flexible and Efficient Reachability Range Assignment for Graph Indexing**.

To be published in: *International Conference on Data Engineering (ICDE 2013)*.

Avishek Anand, Srikanta Bedathur, Klaus Berberich, Ralf Schenkel. Index Maintenance for Time-Travel Text Search. Published in: Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR 2012).

Avishek Anand, Srikanta Bedathur, Klaus Berberich, Ralf Schenkel. **Temporal Index Sharding for Space-Time Efficiency in Archive Search**. Published in: Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR 2011).

Avishek Anand, Srikanta Bedathur, Klaus Berberich, Ralf Schenkel. **Efficient Temporal Keyword Queries over Versioned Text**. Published in: *Proceedings of the 19th ACM Conference on Information and Knowledge Management (CIKM 2010)*.

Avishek Anand, Srikanta Bedathur, Klaus Berberich, Ralf Schenkel, Christos Tryfonopoulos. **EverLast: A Distributed Architecture for Preserving the Web**. Published in: *Joint Conference for Digital Libraries (JCDL 2009)*.

# Teaching Experience

- 2019 Graduate Lecture "Deep Learning " Lecturer.
- 2018 Graduate Lecture "Algorithms for Big Data" Lecturer.
- 2017-2018 Graduate Lecture **"Foundations of Probabilistic IR"** Lecturer.
- 2016-2017, Graduate Lecture "Temporal Information Retrieval"
- 2015-2016 Lecturer.
  - 2016 Graduate Lecture "Large Scale Data Mining" Lecturer.
- 2015-2016 Undergraduate Lecture "Puzzling problems in Computer Science" Lecturer.
  - 2014 Graduate Lecture **"Web Science"** Guest Lecturer.

#### PhD Students

#### Current Jaspreet Singh

Thesis: "Search, Exploration and Interpretability of Temporal Text Collections"

#### Zijian Zhang

Thesis: "Post-hoc Interpretability of Learning Methods"

#### Jurek Leonhardt

Thesis: "Scalable Graph Representations"

#### Graduated Besnik Fetahu

Thesis: "Automatic Wikipedia Reccomendation and Population" (Co-advised with Prof. Wolfgang Nejdl)

#### Helge Holzmann

Thesis: "Large-scale Approaches for Web Archive analysis" (Co-advised with Prof. Wolfgang Neidl)

# Masters' Students Advised/Co-advised

- 2017 Jurek Leonhardt Thesis: "Deep Learning for Citation Detection". [currently a Phd student at L3S
- 2017 Nicolas Tempelmeir Thesis: "Indexing Evolving Graphs". [currently a Phd student at L3S]
- 2014 Jaspreet Singh Thesis: "Diversification for searching News Archives". [currently a PhD student in L3S Research Center]
- 2011 Yagiz Kargin Thesis: "Distributed Analytics over Web Archives". [currently a PhD student in CWI Amsterdam]
- 2012 Bibek Paudel Master Thesis: "Redundancy Control in Web Archives".[currently a PhD student in University of Zurich]
- 2011-2012 Sairam Gurajada Research Topic: "Scaling Graph Clustering". [currently a Senior researcher in IBM Research.]

#### **Professional Activities**

Committee

Organization Dagstuhl Seminar '19 - Conversational Search

Organization WebScience 2016 - Hackathon Chair

Committee

Organizer Alexandria Workshop '16, '17, '18

PC Responsi- SIGIR '19, '18; WWW '19, 18, 17, WSDM '13, '17, '18; CIKM '18, '17; TKDE bilities '12, '14, '15; **TOIS** '18

# Invited Talks/Tutorials

2018 Split, Summer School – "Scaling Text and Graph Representations" **ETH Zürich, Summer School** – "Scalable Word Representations" Weimar University, WEBIS group – "Interpretability of Rankers"

> Appelstrasse 4 – 30167, Hannover, Germany

- **KU Leuven** "Temporal Text Indexing"
- 2017 University of Glasgow, IR group "Wikipedia Enrichment"
- 2016 SIGIR Conference (Tutorial) "Temporal Information Retrieval."
- 2015 University of Bolzano, Department of Database Systems "Temporal Indexing."

# Awards (selected)

- 2019 **Schufa Faculty Award.** Grant for investigating interpretability issues for Machine Learning Models. **Interpretability of Machine Learning models in Finance**.
- 2017-18 **Amazon Research Award.** Grant for investigating interpretability issues for Information Retrieval. **Interpretability of Neural Rankers**.
  - 2016 **Best Paper Award Nomination in JCDL 2016.** Nominated for the Best Paper Award for the paper **ArchiveSpark: Efficient Web Archive Access, Extraction and Derivation**.
  - 2016 **Hannover Impuls Ideenwettbewerb.** Runners up for Hochschul und Wissenschaftspreis for the commercialization potential of a research prototype.
  - 2009 International Max-Planck Research School (IMPRS) Ph.D. scholarship. Awarded to pursue a Ph.D. program at Max Planck Institute for Informatics.
  - 1999 **Indian National Mathematical Olympiad (INMO 1999).** Selected to represent state of Orissa in INMO '99.
    - **Silver Medalist Regional Mathematical Olympiad (RMO 1999).** Silver Medalist and distinction for winning RMO three years in progression.